So today's דף Daf is ו', Vav, we pick up in the
middle of ה עמוד ב'. He Amud Bet. And
I just wanted to just briefly comment on one or two things
that came up yesterday. First we had David's question about why how
to explain the idea that we don't read the מגילה Megillah on
שבת Shabbat because you might carry, why it applies even in the
walled cities? I must say that I did a good amount of
research yesterday and I didn't find anybody that addresses it. So somebody's
got to address it, but you know it is true the גמרא
Gemara does say you can have רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim even in
walled cities, but I was I found it quite fascinating that there
was I could not find certainly in the initial research I did
any material. In terms of the other question about what you do
in terms of משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot and what you do when
the reason you're reading it early is not just because of the
Monday Thursday, but you're reading it early because of שבת. Shabbat. So
here actually what I had said initially was correct that we keep
משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot together with the סעודה. Seudah. And the way
it's done currently in ירושלים Yerushalayim when פורים Purim the fifteenth falls
out on שבת Shabbat is that we read the מגילה Megillah on
the fourteenth, we do the סעודה Seudah and משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot
both of them on the first on Sunday, because it's assumed that
those come together משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot is connected to the סעודה.
Seudah. And the only thing we actually do on the fifteenth on
שבת Shabbat is say על הנסים. Al HaNissim. So it's called משולש
Meshulash not because of so much of like the ritual practices, all
you really have on the fifteenth itself is על הנסים. Al HaNissim.
Interestingly though there are some אחרונים Achronim that strongly argue with this
and say that based on the בבלי Bavli we read that the
שמחה Simchah is בו ביום Bo BaYom that you do the סעודה
Seudah on שבת Shabbat and if you're doing the סעודה Seudah on
שבת Shabbat you even do the משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot on שבת,
Shabbat, even acknowledging David's point that of course if you're not reading
the מגילה Megillah you might come to carry how are you doing
משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot why aren't we concerned you come to carry.
But actually those are the two options. Everybody agrees that the משלוח
מנות Mishloach Manot comes together with the סעודה Seudah and the גמרא
Gemara says the שמחה Simchah is on the normal day but that's
not because of a שבת Shabbat issue. That was when you were
doing it early because of a Monday Thursday. But so there actually
is a fascinating debate in the אחרונים Achronim whether you have the
סעודה Seudah and משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot on שבת Shabbat or the
סעודה Seudah משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot on Sunday and you just have
על הנסים Al HaNissim on שבת. Shabbat. In ירושלים Yerushalayim nowadays the
way they actually do it today in walled cities is is have
the סעודה Seudah with משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot on Sunday so that
addresses any possible carrying issues although the reason given for that is
not the carrying of משלוח מנות, Mishloach Manot, the reason given for
that is the idea that a סעודה Seudah for שמחת פורים Simchat
Purim would somehow be sort of be in competition with the type
of עונג שבת Oneg Shabbat and you want those to be distinct.
So that's the way we do it. מקרא מגילה Mikra Megillah is
Friday, על הנסים Al HaNissim שבת, Shabbat, and the סעודה Seudah and
משלוח מנות. Mishloach Manot. That's when the fifteenth is on a שבת.
Shabbat. That's when the fifteenth is on a שבת. Shabbat. In theory
the same with the fourteenth except that never happens with our calendar.
Okay so in a walled city on שבת Shabbat what? In a
walled city well yeah but that gets back to then David's question
which is why and why aren't we reading the מגילה Megillah on
שבת? Shabbat? If you do משלוח מנות Mishloach Manot on שבת Shabbat
might as well read the מגילה. Megillah. All right so now let's
resume and get move forward. Let's go get back to ה עמוד
ב' He Amud Bet here. Oh yeah you were going to say
but you know let's just hold it I'm sorry. Let's get back
to ה עמוד ב' He Amud Bet we're already a good bit
behind. And the גמרא Gemara says like this, ורבי, V'Rabbi, it is
about eight lines from the top of ה עמוד ב' He Amud
Bet and we had a story with a couple of interesting things
that Rabbi did but one of them was that he planted something
on פורים. Purim. And this is now going to get us to
the question of in addition to the observances we've just mentioned מקרא
מגילה, Mikra Megillah, מתנות
לאביונים, Matanot LaEvyonim, סעודה Seudah and משלוח מנות, Mishloach Manot, is there
an idea of not doing מלאכה Melachah on פורים? Purim? Presumably
we don't mean like שבת Shabbat but maybe something like חול המועד
Chol HaMoed right a day where there is a limited amount that
you do in terms of the מלאכה. Melachah. So the גמרא Gemara
asks it. It says ורבי היכי נטע בפורים? V'Rabbi Heichi Nata B'Purim?
How did Rabbi plant something on פורים? Purim? והתניא רב יוסף, V'Hatanya
Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef teaches in a ברייתא, Baraita, שמחה
ומשתה ויום טוב, Simchah U'Mishteh V'Yom Tov,
it says by פורים Purim that לעשות אותם ימי משתה ושמחה ויום
טוב? La'asot Otam Yemei Mishteh V'Simchah V'Yom Tov? Yeah. Okay. ומשלוח מנות
איש לרעהו. U'Mishloach Manot Ish L'Re'ehu. Right so it says
that to make them days of rejoicing and drinking, of course that's
the other thing about פורים Purim that we have to get to,
and a יום טוב. Yom Tov. שמחה מלמד שאסור בהספד. Simchah Melamed
She'Asur B'Hesped. שמחה Simchah tells you that you cannot do a eulogy.
It's telling you what you don't do, you don't do things that
undermine שמחה. Simchah. משתה מלמד שאסור בתענית. Mishteh Melamed She'Asur B'Ta'anit. And
a משתה Mishteh means that you're not allowed to fast. It's interesting
that it hasn't said from either of those that there's an idea
of of course having a סעודת פורים, Seudat Purim, but okay anyway
that's the איסור הספד ותענית. Issur Hesped V'Ta'anit. And what does יום
טוב Yom Tov tell you? יום טוב Yom Tov מלמד שאסור בעשיית
מלאכה. Melamed She'Asur B'Asiyat Melachah. That you can't do מלאכה. Melachah. Fascinating
how each one of those things translates into what you don't do
not what you do do. Anyway according to that ברייתא Baraita you
don't do מלאכה Melachah on פורים. Purim. אלא Ella so how do
we explain how Rabbi made this planting? אלא רבי בר ארביסר הוה.
Ella Rabbi Bar Arbatzar Hava. No no no here so first we
accept the premise you don't do מלאכה Melachah on פורים Purim but
Rabbi was from an unwalled city, דכי נטע בחמיסר הוה. DeChinata B'Chamishar
Assar Hava. how each one of those things translates into what you
don't do, not what you do did. Anyway, according to that ברייתא,
Braisa, you don't do מלאכה Melacha on פורים. Purim. and not that,
and when he planted he planted on the 15th, there wasn't פורים
Purim then. There wasn't פורים Purim then. Right. So, yeah, he, when
he said he planted on פורים, Purim, he didn't really mean his
פורים. Purim. איני, Eini, is that really true? והא רבי מטבריה הוה,
Ve-ha Rebbe mi-Tverya havei, we know רבי Rebbe comes from Tiberia. וטבריה
מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון היא, Ve-Tverya mukefes chomah mi-yemot Yehoshua
bin Nun hi, and we know Tiberia, which we'll get to later
in the גמרא, Gemara, was surrounded by a wall from the time
of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun. So they must have... Okay,
whip it. אלא רבי בר חמיסר הוה. Ella Rebbe bar chamesar havei.
Fine, he was from the 15th, a place that reads on the
15th. וכי נטע בארבעה עשר הוה, Ve-ki natah be-arba-asar havei, and he
planted on the 14th. It's still the same answer. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, no, no, that's not going to work here. Why
not? מי פשיטא דטבריה מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון? Mi pshita
de-Tverya mukefes chomah mi-yemot Yehoshua bin Nun? If it's so obvious that
Tiberia the wall did exist from the time of יהושע בן נון?
Yehoshua bin Nun? והא חזקיה קרי בטבריה בארבעה עשר ובחמישה עשר, Ve-ha
Chizkiya kari bi-Tverya be-arba-asar u-ve-chamesar, חזקיה Chizkiya read in Tiberia
on the 14th and the 15th. מספקא ליה Misafka lei because he
had a doubt אם מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון היא אי
לא, im mukefes chomah mi-yemot Yehoshua bin Nun hi, i lo, whether
it was surrounded by a wall. So this issue came up: how
do you know if it satisfied the criteria? So if there's any
serious doubt, presumably, and this is how we פוסקים, pasken, you read
on both. He read on the 14th and the 15th. I'll just
say parenthetically that when that happens, the ברכה bracha you make is
on the 14th because the 14th is assumed to be the norm.
The 15th is treated as the exception, right? Which makes sense just
in terms of the numbers. And also the fact that the מגילה
Megillah basically speaks about the reading of the 14th. על כן הפרזים
היושבים קוראים, Al kein ha-perazim ha-yoshvim korim, you know, עושים יום ארבעה
עשר בו. osim yom arba-asar bo. So it doesn't even explicitly mention
what the non-perazim do. So in those scenarios you read on both,
but you make the ברכות brachas on the 14th. Okay, that's not...
the ברכות brachas aren't discussed here. But anyway, so חזקיה Chizkiya read
on both. So רבי Rebbe would have had to have treated both
of them as the holiday. So what does the גמרא Gemara say?
So the גמרא Gemara says לחזקיה מספקא ליה. le-Chizkiya misafka lei.
Fine, חזקיה Chizkiya had a doubt. לרבי פשיטא ליה. Le-Rebbe pshita lei.
רבי Rebbe
assumed that it was obvious that Tiberia was from the day... was
a walled city. וכי פשיטא ליה מישרי? Ve-chi pshita lei mishari? And
therefore he planted on the 14th because that wasn't his פורים. Purim.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. וכי פשיטא ליה מישרי? Ve-chi
pshita lei mishari? Just because it's obvious to him
that he's from a walled city and he does the 15th, since
when is there no status to the 14th?
Even in walled cities? והא כתיב במגילת תענית, Ve-ha ketiv bi-Megillas Taanis,
it's written in מגילת תענית, Megillas Taanis, את יום ארבעה עשר ואת
יום חמישה עשר, es yom arba-asar ve-es yom chamishoh asar, right,
quoting the מגילה. Megillah. It says that you know observe the 14th
and the 15th. So the מגילת תענית Megillas Taanis says ימי פורים
אינון. yemei Purim inun. These are the days of פורים, Purim, right?
We've learned all about מגילת תענית Megillas Taanis in מסכת תענית, Masechet
Taanis, the listing of the minor holidays. And even though you know
the basic assumption is that we don't keep all those minor holidays
anymore, the ones that we do keep are still פורים Purim and
חנוכה. Chanukah. And the basic point about listing minor holidays in מגילת
תענית Megillas Taanis is to tell you that you cannot have a
הספד hesped and a תענית. taanis. So ימי פורים אינון, yemei Purim
inun, those are the days of פורים, Purim, דלא למספד בהון, de-lo
le-misped be-hon, that you don't do eulogizing on those days and you
don't have a fast day. So and אמר רבא, amar Rava, now
what does that tell you? That presumably means 14th for unwalled and
15th for walled. But רבא Rava says, no. לא נצרכה אלא לאסור
דזה בזה ודזה בזה. Lo nitzrecha ella le-asur de-zeh be-zeh ve-de-zeh be-zeh.
He says why does it have to even be mentioned in מגילת
תענית? Megillas Taanis? It's already mentioned in the מגילה. Megillah. So the
only reason מגילת תענית Megillas Taanis repeats the days of פורים Purim
is to tell you that the 14th and 15th come as a
package, that regardless of whether you're from a walled city or an
unwalled city, you have to observe the 14th and the 15th as
days of not having a הספד hesped and a תענית. taanis. So
the גמרא Gemara is assuming if you're anyway going to observe, it's
like we don't say תחנון Tachanun on שושן פורים. Shushan Purim. So
if you're anyway not going to have a הספד hesped and a
תענית taanis on the 14th and the 15th, presumably if there's an
idea of not doing מלאכה, melacha, that should also apply on both
days. So the גמרא Gemara gives the obvious answer. The גמרא Gemara
says no, הני מילי בהספד ובתענית. hani mili be-hesped u-ve-taanis.
That's only הספד hesped and תענית taanis that you observe both days
regardless of where you're from. אבל מלאכה, Aval melacha, but when it
comes to not doing מלאכה melacha on פורים, Purim, יום אחד ותו
לא, yom echad u-tu lo, only on your day of observance you
not do מלאכה, melacha, not on the others. And the גמרא... Gemara...
no, no, no, because the גמרא Gemara is going to reject the
whole idea that there's an איסור מלאכה. issur melacha. So all of
this is still working with the premise that you don't do מלאכה
melacha on פורים Purim and saying רבי Rebbe was doing מלאכה melacha
on the other day. And even though we observe the other day
in terms of not doing הספד hesped and תענית, taanis, we do
not do... it does not have a status in terms of not
doing מלאכה. melacha. Now, your סוגיא sugia is shaky. The whole thing
is based on a ספק ספיקא. sfek sfeka. You don't know if
it's the 14th or the 15th. You don't know if מלאכה melacha
is... No, no, no, no, no. First of all, it's not a
ספקא. sfeka. The גמרא Gemara is assuming a premise that you don't
do מלאכה. melacha. You're saying well maybe not, but the גמרא Gemara
is assuming that that is true. We don't do it. The פסוק
pasuk says ימי משתה ושמחה ויום טוב, yemei mishteh ve-simcha ve-yom tov,
שמחה ומשתה ויום טוב. simcha ve-mishteh ve-yom tov. And the גמרא Gemara
is assuming that רבי Rebbe knows that טבריה Tverya is the 15th.
So although there's other opinions out there, it doesn't mean we have
to concern ourselves with them. That's the assumption the גמרא Gemara is
working with. I should just say quickly, sort of parenthetically, if you
look at תוספות, Tosfos, he... given that we've learned all of מסכת
תענית, Masechet Taanis, this idea of not doing
הספד... hesped... And then this little תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* here problematizes the
whole thing. Look at this תוספות *Tosfos*, השיב רש״י Rashi *Hishiv Rashi*,
תוספות *Tosfos* says השיב רש״י *Hishiv Rashi*, so apparently there's a תשובה
*Teshuvah* of רש״י *Rashi*, וכי מינתן כח לימי מגילת אסתר לדחות אבילות
aveilus. *ve-khi mintan koach li-yemei Megillat Esther lidchos aveilus*? Rashi says so
since when does a מגילה Megilla *Megillah* come along, you know somebody,
somebody died, you know you want to say a הספד hesped *Hesped*,
so why should the מגילה Megilla *Megillah* override the idea of אבילות
aveilus *aveilus*? Which is a fascinating question, I mean since when is
the need to say a הספד hesped *Hesped*, it's one thing to
say not to do the biblical observance of אבילות aveilus *aveilus*, though
the whole question how much of אבילות aveilus *aveilus* is biblical at
all if anything, some of the observances of the first day, but
we're just saying don't do a הספד *Hesped*. But רש״י *Rashi* writes
in a תשובה *Teshuvah*, how does the מגילה Megilla, *Megillah* have the
power to tell us not to do a הספד *Hesped*, not to
do an observance of אבילות aveilus *aveilus*? I mean it's fascinating because
all of מגילת תענית Ta'anit, *Megillat Taanis* is about not doing הספדים
hespedim *Hespedim*, right? And those are even much more minor days. And
here the whole point we've been making is the tremendous weight that
חז״ל *Chazal* give the מגילה Megilla *Megillah* and the tremendous authority that
they give it. And here's the challenge that רש״י *Rashi* is raising.
The reason he's raised that challenge, as we'll see, is because that
wasn't because people were ignoring that, that in practice people were giving
הספדים *Hespedim* on פורים Purim? *Purim*. So therefore רש״י *Rashi*, you know
it's this classic thing of how do you do when the observance
contradicts the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, so רש״י *Rashi* problematizes the statement in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Since when do you should you not be
saying a הספד *Hesped* just because of the מגילה Megilla *Megillah*? And
what's the original תשובה *Teshuvah*? Where is that? Yeah I did not
check, we do have תשובות רש״י *Teshuvos Rashi*. I thought he talks
about the 11th, 12th, and 13th. וכי מינתן כח לימי מגילת אסתר
*ve-khi mintan koach li-yemei Megillat Esther*. He adds ימי מגילת אסתר *yemei
Megillat Esther* would be I'd say 14th and 15th, I don't see
why ימי *yemei* just all of פורים Purim, *Purim*. Yeah but that
would be ימי *yemei*, I don't know, מגילת אסתר *Megillat Esther* not
מסכת *Masechet*, I don't know, מגילה Megilla *Megillah* is the days on
which you read the... oh
that's interesting although that's not what's being referred to here. I hear
that, that's interesting. I'll have to check, I'll have to check if
we have the original.
Yeah right right right. Okay. And then he says ועוד איתא דהספד
נאסר משום דכתיב de-chtiv ימי משתה ושמחה *ve-od ista de-hesped ne-esar mishum
de-chtiv yemei mishte ve-simcha*. So here that's going to the מגילה Megilla,
*Megillah*. If you say it's אסור assur בהספד *assur be-hesped*, והחזינא דכויי
עמא נהגו בו היתר heter. *ve-hachazina de-choi amma nahagu bo heter*. Right?
So this is clearly what's motivating the תשובה *Teshuvah*. Everybody gives a
הספד *Hesped*. אלא ודאי לא הוה אלא עניין שאין נופלים על פניהם
דלא הוה יום צרה אלא יום שמחה simcha *ella vadai lo hava
ella inyan she-ein noflim al pneihem de-lo hava yom tzara ella yom
simcha*. So it doesn't really mean you don't do a הספד *Hesped*
on פורים Purim *Purim*, it just means you don't say תחנון *Tachanun*.
So it's fascinating, we learned all of מסכת תענית ta'anit *Masechet Taanis*,
all of these days that you don't do הספד *Hesped* and תענית
*Taanis*, and here רש״י *Rashi* because people basically were ignoring that... Now
the fact that people ignored the rest of מגילת תענית *Megillat Taanis*
was not a problem because we say בטלה מגילת תענית *batla Megillat
Taanis*. But the days that were left with of אסור assur, בהספד
ותענית *assur be-hesped ve-taanis* is פורים Purim *Purim* and חנוכה Chanukah *Chanukah*.
So then presumably price... I mean if it applies to פורים Purim.
*Purim* it should certainly apply to חנוכה *Chanukah*. So I just want
to point out this fascinating thing of undermining this whole idea of
אסור בהספד *assur be-hesped* because the practice was to give הספדים *Hespedim*
on פורים Purim *Purim* and רש״י *Rashi* says eh it just means
don't say תחנון *Tachanun*, doesn't mean... Does that mean they had תחנון
*Tachanun* at the time? I don't know. Alright so now let's continue,
it's a good point too. So back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying that it still is... there
is an איסור מלאכה issur melacha? *issur melacha* but it only applies
to your day itself not the other day. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says אבל avel מלאכה melacha יום אחד ושניהו לא *aval melacha
yom echad u-shneihu lo*? איני *eini*, is that really true? Opposite the
תוספות *Tosfos* where it says דברים Devarim *de-varim*. והא רב Rav, חזיה
לגברא דהוה כשדי כיתנא בפוריא *ve-ha Rav chazya le-gavra de-hava kashadi kitna
be-puraya*, Rav saw a certain person that was planting flax on פורים
Purim, *Purim*, לטייה *lafyei* and he cursed him, ולא צמח כיתנא *ve-lo
tzmach kitneih* and as a result presumably the flax didn't sprout. So
how could you say it's allowed on the other day? So there's
an obvious answer, he said that was the other day. השתא בר
יומי הוה *hasham bar yomei hava*, that was the guy's own day
of פורים Purim *Purim*, it wasn't the other day. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says רבה בריה דרב אמר *ve-Rabba bereih de-Rav amar*... so
so far with all this we're saying there's an איסור מלאכה issur
melacha *issur melacha* on פורים Purim. *Purim*. Amazing. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ורבה בריה דרב אמר *ve-Rabba bereih de-Rav amar* now רבה
*Rabba* the son of רב Rav *Rav* says אפילו
תימא ביומי *afilu tima be-yomei*, even רב Rav *Rav* could have done
the planting even on the day of פורים Purim *Purim* itself. הספד
ותענית קבילו עלייהו *hesped ve-taanis kibilu aleihu*, that in...
at the end of the day, you know at the final stage
the Jews agreed to accept the ימי משתה ושמחה *yemei mishte ve-simcha*,
the הספד *hesped* and the תענית *taanis*. מלאכה melacha לא קבילו עלייהו
*melacha lo kibilu aleihu*, they never accepted it as a day of
איסור מלאכה issur melacha. *issur melacha*. How do you... so right, so
how do you... so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s going to ask so
why did רב Rav *Rav* react? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
דמעיקרא כתיב שמחה simcha. ומשתה ויום טוב *de-mei-ikara ktiv simcha u-mishte ve-yom
tov*. It says that you know מרדכי *Mordechai* and אסתר *Esther* sent
that they should make these days of פורים Purim *Purim* לעשות אותם
ימי משתה ושמחה ויום טוב ומשלוח מנות איש לרעהו *la-asot otam yemei
mishte ve-simcha ve-yom tov u-mishloach manos ish le-reeihu*. So initially it says
that they... the message was you should make this into a יום
טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. ולבסוף כתיב קימו וקבלו היהודים עליהם ועל
זרעם להיות עושים את ימי הפורים האלה לעשות אותם ימי משתה ושמחה
*u-le-vasof ktiv kiyemu ve-kiblu Ha-Yehudim aleihem ve-al zaram lihyos osim es yemei
ha-Purim ha-eleh la-asot otam yemei mishte ve-simcha*. ויום טוב *ve-yom tov*, אילו
יום טוב Yom Tov לא כתיב *ilu yom tov lo ktiv*. So
when מרדכי *Mordechai* says I want you to make this into a
יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, מרדכי ואסתר *Mordechai ve-Esther*. The Jews
said we'll accept it as ימי משתה ושמחה *yemei mishte ve-simcha*, not
a יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* we don't need. So in
the end that פורים *Purim* is not אסור במלאכה assur be'melacha. *assur
be-melacha*. Now I want to say something. First of all it's fascinating
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it waited from the time of a
statement by what רב rav *Rav* did until the time of רב
*Rav*... statement, the גמרא Gemara was dealing with the idea and the
premise that it's אסור במלאכה. So what were people doing during פורים?
Nobody ever had a need to do a מלאכה melacha? from the
time of רבי Rebbe till רב, and then רב says oh by
the way they were never מקבל mekabel it on themselves as an
איסור מלאכה? issur melacha Like I just really don't even understand, like
you know doing a מלאכה melacha is a natural thing that would
come up. You got a lot of free time on פורים, right?
So it's not like you're busy reading the מגילה Megillah the whole
day. So I don't even understand like למעשה lema'aseh were people doing
work on פורים or not? Maybe they weren't doing it but the
question was were they strictly forbidden or was it just a מנהג
minhag not to do מלאכה? melacha. So that's just question number one.
Point number two is that I think this is very important because
as I said a whole challenge, the whole issue that sort of
runs through the מגילה Megilla, is the authority of creating a new
type of a holiday, right? In fact the מגילה, Megilla, the idea
of the מגילה is very late and becoming one of the ספרי
תנ״ך, Sifrei Tanakh, the authority of the verses in the מגילה to
obligate various practices, all of those issues. So I think it is
significant though that פורים and מגילה which are the two late holidays
are at least not ימים טובים. yamim tovim. Don't have the real
weight of a יום טוב. Yom Tov. You know they're days that
you do special observances with, you say על הנסים, Al HaNissim, you
light candles, you read the מגילה, but even when we're innovating new
holidays we're not turning them into a יום טוב Yom Tov. which
I think would have required a whole other level of authority. So
I don't just think it's a technical point among the other things,
do we do מלאכה melacha. or not do מלאכה. melacha, It really
gets to a very deep point to the character of the day.
Okay, so that is what the גמרא Gemara? says and that is
our conclusion that there is no איסור מלאכה issur melacha on פורים.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואלא רב מאי טעמא
לטייה לההוא גברא, ve'ella Rav mai ta'ama latyei le'hahu gavra, so then
why did רב curse this גברא? gavra? Right? I mean there's no
איסור מלאכה. issur melacha So דברים המותרים ואחרים נהגו בהן איסור. devarim
ha'mutarim v'acherim nahagu bahen issur. Yes, technically it was מותר mutar but
in that place people had a מנהג minhag not to do it
and that as I said might explain how the גמרא Gemara had
this whole question you know about whether because in practice generally people
don't do מלאכה. melacha So the question is is that a strict
halachic obligation or is that just a מנהג? minhag? So רב was
in a place where that was the מנהג minhag ובאתריה דרב u'be'asrei
de'Rav and therefore he cursed him just because he was violating the
מנהג. minhag. So but how about what רבי Rebbe did, רבי Rebbe
planted? ובאתריה
דרבי לא נהוג u'be'asrei de'Rebbe lo nahug in רבי's Rebbe place they
didn't have that מנהג minhag or maybe רבי Rebbe was trying to
teach people that it's just a מנהג, minhag, it's not a real
הלכה. halacha. ואיבעית אימא v'iba'is eima if you want לעולם נהוג. le'olam
nahug. Maybe in רבי's Rebbe place they did have the מנהג. minhag.
So then why did רבי Rebbe go ahead and plant? Why wasn't
he violating the
מנהג? minhag? ורבי נטיעה של שמחה נטע, ve'Rebbe netiya shel simcha nata,
he planted a planting of שמחה simcha which maybe the idea of
איסור מלאכה issur melacha. and here the גמרא's Gemara saying even within
the מנהג minhag of איסור מלאכה issur melacha it wasn't איסור מלאכה
issur melacha in the type of יום טוב Yom Tov. way of
איסור מלאכה. issur melacha You know like for example they say להבדיל
le'havdil that an אבל avel also is not supposed to do מלאכה,
melacha right? But that doesn't mean you can't turn on the light,
light a match. You mean you don't involve yourselves in other types
of professional activities which distracts the אבל from the אבילות. So but
not like it's an איסור מלאכה issur melacha of the יום טוב
Yom Tov, or even from the חול המועד chol ha'moed category. So
here too, the איסור issur מלאכה melacha, is to take you away
from שמחה. simcha. To do a מלאכה melacha in terms of that
שמחה simcha related, that would be okay. Okay? And again the גמרא
Gemara... here brings an example from the opposite area, from a more
of an אבילות category. So let's take a look. תניא
נמי tanya nami like we taught in the משנה, Mishna, עברו אלו
ולא נענו avru elu v'lo na'anu see that's tying us into תענית,
these days passed, all the fast days passed and they still were
not answered.
עברו ולא נענו, avru v'lo na'anu, ממעטין במשא ומתן בבנין ובנטיעה באירוסין
ובנישואין. mema'atin be'massa u'mattan be'vinyan u've'netiya be'eirusin u'vi'nisu'in. You minimize the amount
of business dealings that you do, the construction
and planting, betrothals and marriages. Okay and you don't do all of
this because it's more
you sort of go from a תענית mode to more of an
אבילות type of a mode. ותני עלה ve'tani ala and we explained
בנין, binyan, what does it mean by בנין? binyan? בנין של שמחה.
binyan shel simcha. You don't do a type of a construction that
has joy associated with it. נטיעה netiya and planting, נטיעה של שמחה.
netiya shel simcha. איזו היא בנין של שמחה? eizo hi binyan shel
simcha? What's a construction of joy? זה הבונה בית חתנות לבנו ze
ha'boneh beit chasnut li'vno that you're building a wedding house for your
son. So for רש״י says first son gets married, you build a
whole house with a חופה chuppa and the whole thing and it's
obviously a very joyous type of a thing. ואיזו היא נטיעה של
שמחה? ve'eizo hi netiya shel simcha? What's a planting of joy? זה
הנוטע אבורנקי של מלכים, ze ha'noteia avroneki shel melachim, a type of
a garden for kings, you know a type of a park, something
that's a gazebo, well that would be a בנין binyan not a
נטיעה, netiya, but you know something that's really there that's very much
about enjoyment and pleasure and so on. So what does that have
to do? That's about an איסור issur not a היתר. But it's
saying there is this thing, this phenomenon called נטיעה של שמחה, netiya
shel simcha, a halachic thing that's recognized as בנין של שמחה binyan
shel simcha and נטיעה של שמחה. netiya shel simcha. And the point
I would make is what I just said, that that's a type
of a thing which is אסור to do in an אבילות type
of a mode because it takes you away from an אבילות and
by פורים you... get the flip side, you say don't do מלאכה
melacha even with the מנהג, minhag, we're no longer doing with the
הלכה, halacha, but even the מנהג minhag of don't do מלאכה, melacha
it's not don't do מלאכה melacha because it's a quasi יום טוב.
Yom Tov Don't do מלאכה because it takes you away from the
שמחה. simcha. So a מלאכה that is about שמחה simcha, would be
allowed. So and therefore רבי Rebbi could do the נטיעה של שמחה.
niteiya shel simcha. So I think again what's fascinating is that even
within the מנהג, minhag, we're not treating the מנהג minhag of איסור
מלאכה as let's treat this as a quasi יום טוב. We're treating
the איסור of a מנהג minhag of the איסור מלאכה as let's
not distract ourselves from the שמחה. simcha. And again that gets to
the issue of the character of the day of not making the
day with what all that we're doing with creating פורים, we're not
making it even within this מנהג minhag mode, we're not making it
a יום טוב. David, you had a question? Or a quasi? Yeah.
So are they are they saying here that נטיעה של שמחה niteiya
shel simcha
that these are things that actually are not that are not commercial?
They're extravagances. Is is that what they're saying? I don't mean extravagance,
I think it's something that I mean I think it's just something
that evokes joy. Why are you like recategorizing this extravagance rather than
just specifically joy related? Well let's say we have expensive weddings today,
imagine if you had to build a house for the people as
well. Right. And it's not it's not you're not building something to
put into the realm of commerce, you're building something as Right, I
I understand that but I don't think that that's I don't think
it's it's just about not being commerce. I mean I think it
is true, it's like funny like you're building a whole house like
you know that's like a major type of an expense, but you
know it might have meant something less substantial, it might have meant
like you know I don't know imagine like building a gazebo to
get married under, you know and a special trellis gazebo or something
like that. Are you thinking of a temporary structure? You're thinking of
a permanent structure? No, I mean from רש"י Rashi it sounds like
he's assuming it's a permanent structure. But I hear your point, but
again I don't see a need to sort of reframe it, I
think the גמרא Gemara is specifically talking about the fact that it
evokes שמחה, yes, here and also in the context if I remember
correctly planting as נטיעה niteiya during the nine days or during תשעה
באב. Tisha B'Av. So is like an it's a tree that that
gives you a lot of shade or pleasurable to sit under? This
is a really naive question, but you don't plant a tree that
size, so you're talking about planting the sapling that will grow into
such a tree? Oh, that's an interesting question. Could be, just because
of the of the emotion that accompanies what type of a thing
that you're doing. Right, although with רש"י, Rashi, I get a sense
from רש"י Rashi we're also talking about like you have like a
whole trellis, you have like a whole like you know what they
do like they have this thing in the in Wave Hill or
whatever, you know you've got this like trellis walkway with a roof
to it as well and the vines go on top of the
trellis, and that's sort of the way רש"י Rashi describes it. So
I guess some of that you could get in place even initially.
But yeah. All right, anyway that's the point. So what we have
is is that presumably and this is why the גמרא Gemara could
have a question if it's really אסור, the general practice was not
to really do so much, you know מלאכה on פורים and in
the end we say it's not because it has a status of
a יום טוב, דחיי דלא קבילו, de-chai de-lo kiblu, and to the
degree that it exists it's a מנהג minhag and as I've been
saying in terms of this last point, even the מנהג minhag was
not a יום טוב type of a מנהג, minhag, it was more
about distracting yourself from the שמחה. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara.
continues. גופא. Gufa. Second line in the wide lines. חזקיה קרי בטבריא
בארביסר ובחמיסר. Chizkiyah kari bi-Tveriah be-arveisar u-ve-chamisar. Let's let's go back to
that earlier statement. חזקיה Chizkiyah read in טבריה Tveriah on the fourteenth
and the fifteenth. מספקא ליה, Mesapka lei, he had his doubt אי
מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון היא אי לאו, ei mukafes chomah
mi-yemos Yehoshua bin Nun hi ei lav, was it a walled city
from the time of Joshua. ומספקא
ליה? U-mesapka lei? How could he have a doubt? says the גמרא.
Gemara מילתא דטבריא, Milta de-Tveriah, the issue of טבריה. Tveriah. והכתיב, Ve-haksiv,
and the verse says וערים מבצר הצדים
צר וחמת רקת וכנרת. ve-arim mivtzar ha-Tzidim Tzer ve-Chamas Rekas ve-Chinneres. That
was a list of walled cities in יהושע. Yehoshua. Now what are
these cities? וקיימא לן, Ve-kayma lan, we have we have established, as
we'll discuss momentarily, רקת זו טבריה, Rekas zo Tveriah, that רקת Rekas
is טבריה. Tveriah. So it says it's a walled city, fortified city.
הגמרא Ha-Gemara says well היינו טעמא דמספקא ליה. hainu ta'ama de-mesapka lei.
Here's the reason. משום דחד גיסא שורא דימא הוה. mishum de-chad gisa
shura de-yama hava. One side of טבריה Tveriah is not a wall,
it has it's on the water. It's by so אי הכי, ei
hachi, so then and the question is does that count as a
wall or not? I'm sorry, wait, so the other three sides were
walls? Three sides were walls, but it's not completely surrounded. So the
גמרא says אי הכי אמאי מספקא ליה? ei hachi amai mesapka lei?
So what's the doubt? ודאי לאו חומה היא. Vadai lav chomah hi.
It doesn't count as a wall. דתניא, De-tanya, and again borrowing the
idea of walled cities from another area of הלכה. halacha. אשר לו
חומה, Asher lo chomah, that has a wall. This is by house
in a walled city for יובל Yovel laws. ולא שור איגר, Velo
shur igar,
and not a wall of roofs. So what רש"י Rashi says that
means is not a wall created by building houses like townhouses, by
building houses all one against the other. It has to be a
wall that is created like that stands separate, that's not just created
by the houses. סביב, Saviv, a wall around, פרט לטבריה, perat le-Tveriah,
the ברייתא braisa explicitly says טבריה Tveriah does not count as a
walled city for of houses in walled cities of יובל *Yovel*. שימה
חומתה *sheyamma chomatah* that it's the ocean is its you know the
water is its its wall. So you see that it does not
count.
About that- well that's the point. It has to go all the
way around. So מסכת *Masechet*- look. ענין בתי ערי חומה *inyan battei
arei chomah* for houses in a walled city לא מספקא ליה *lo
mesafke leh*. You're right, wouldn't have a doubt. There's an idea of
סביב *saviv*. כי קא מספקא ליה לענין מקרא מגילה *ki ga mesafke
leh le'inyan mikra Megillah*. The doubt is about מגילה *Megillah*. So here
for the first time the גמרא *Gemara* is saying you can't totally
borrow the pre-existing category by בתי ערי חומה *battei arei chomah*. Now
תוספות *Tosafot* discusses we still borrow it a lot, but we might
not be able to borrow it 100% to just apply that category.
Now why would this be a reason to make a distinction here?
Because here's the question. And the way רשי Rashi *Rashi* says it
is to emphasize the פסוקים psukim *psukim* by מגילה *Megillah* don't identify
walled cities, they identify the opposite. They identify unwalled. So you know
this is a point that I always make right, the opposite of
vanilla is not chocolate, it's like not vanilla. Right, if you say
well vanilla and chocolate there's a lot of things that are between
the two. So what are you defining? Are you defining walled cities
or are you defining unwalled? If you're defining walled cities, right so
that's going to be the smaller category, something has to satisfy a
lot of criteria to be a walled city, right? There's walled city
here and unwalled city here and there's a lot of things between
them that are not exactly walled and not exactly unwalled like טבריה
Tverya *Tverya* that has three walls but has the ocean and has
other things. So if the פסוקים psukim. *psukim* are defining walled cities,
so well that doesn't- טבריה Tverya. *Tverya* doesn't satisfy, it doesn't have
a wall all around. But if the פסוקים *psukim* are talking about
unwalled cities, unwalled cities contrasted to the un-unwalled cities, I mean the
opposite of the walled ones, so then maybe those middle cases
would qualify because they're not in the category of unwalled. The one
that you
define usually is the smaller category because there's a much bigger universe
out there of not A than A tends to be. Have they
been built to walls because of security? Ah excellent. So that's exactly
what the גמרא *Gemara* is going to ask. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לענין מקרא מגילה *le'inyan mikra Megillah*
איבעיא ליה *ibaye leh* unwalled and the opposite of unwalled. מאי פרוזים
ומאי מוקפין *mai pruzim u'mai mukkafin*. What does it mean to be
unwalled? What does it mean to be walled? דכתיב גבי מקרא מגילה
*de'chtiv gabei mikra Megillah*. משום- so what I just said of emphasizing
unwalled, that's what רשי Rashi *Rashi* says, that's not so much emphasized
pointed out in the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay but anyway here's the question.
משום דהני מיגלו והני לא מיגלו *mishum de'hanu miglu ve'hanu lo miglu*
and but you sort of see it in the גמרא *Gemara*. It
starts with the idea of פרוזים *pruzim*. פרוזים *pruzim* the idea is
exposed. So it's a difference between being exposed and not being exposed.
והני נמי מיגליה *ve'hani nami mighalya* and טבריה Tverya. *Tverya* is also
exposed. It's like you know it's not blocked off from view, you
can see one side of it, it's not surrounded by a wall.
So maybe פרוזים *pruzim* means like it's you know protected from view-
unprotected from view, exposed, and that would be true about טבריה Tverya
*Tverya*. או דילמא משום דהני מיגנו mignu והני לא מיגנו mignu, *o
dilma mishum de'hani mignu ve'hani lo mignu*. Maybe the issue is whether
they are like in terms of a security way are they protected
or not. Not protected from view, not exposed, but actually defended and
protected. So walled cities are more protected. והא נמי מיגנו mignu, *ve'ha
nami mignu* and טבריה Tverya *Tverya* is protected because it's got a
wall and it's got water. Yeah so you can have a wall
only on one side right depending on what the topography- Right what
about if you had an
island? Right good question. What's the limit? Right. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says משום הכי מספקא ליה *mishum hachi mesafke leh* and that's why
he has a doubt. Okay so one thing is just the interesting
formalist point that I made about are we defining walled or are
we defining unwalled. But the other question comes up like why should
these issues matter, exposed versus protected and so on. And what I'll
say here and it's requires more elaboration but I didn't say it
initially is you know רמבן Ramban *Ramban* raises this big question and
that I've been raising with you which is why the heck would
we create two separate holidays? You know for the 14th and the
15th. Why would we ever do this? And what רמבן *Ramban* says
is and the way he wants to- and he has a whole
way of reading the last few פרקים *perakim* in מגילה *Megillah* of
the מגילה *Megillah* itself. But his basic theory is the following. He
says against the גמרא *Gemara*'s assumption that the story of מגילה *Megillah*
occurred once the בנין בית שני *binyan bayit sheni* already began, not
between the two בנין בית *binyan bayit*. And therefore he says number
one you know that meant the- you know that led to this
whole question about whether the Jews in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz
Yisrael* like you know were they under threat as well and that's
sort of a way of tying in the whole issue about מימות
יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun. *mi-yemot Yehoshua bin Nun* type of
an issue and our relationship to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael*.
That's sort of one point. But the other point he also makes
is that he believes that you know when the- when they were
going to war against their enemies in the story of the מגילה
*Megillah*, those weren't the enemies from within like their own townspeople, those
were people from without. I don't know why- how he can imagine
this. As if you had a city that was all Jews and
the question was being attacked from another city that wasn't Jewish. So
therefore he says the significance of being מוקף חומה *mukkaf chomah* was
that you were more defended and maybe you didn't feel that you
were under the threat. And therefore he says, and therefore the רמב"ן
wants to read that initially, because notice the פסוקים only say that
the פרזים prazim observe. It doesn't say what the non-פרזים prazim did.
So the רמב"ן claims that initially the non-פרזים prazim said, "We don't
have to keep this פורים. It's not a holiday for us, you
know, we were protected, we had a wall." So they didn't even
want to keep it. And then sort of, you know, Mordechai insisted
that they keep it or whatever and then finally they adopted and
then they agreed to keep it, but initially they sort of were
resisting keeping the whole thing altogether. He reads the מגילה this way
like a close reading of the פסוקים. Again it imagines a certain
historical circumstance which I'm not sure is can really be accepted, but
anyway that's the way he understands it. So he says and that's
why to have this distinct day
because of like initial history and why the גמרא even has a
bizarre question, maybe the 15th don't observe it at all. So it
says אטו הני לאו ישראל נינהו? Atu hanu lav Yisrael ninhu? What?
Are they not Jews? You know but he says well what happened
to them was what you know maybe they didn't experience the miracle
so much and in the end they're doing it but they're sort
of recognizing it's all part of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael and we
all connected but at the same time
our experience of this whole story was very different than yours. So
he says and that's why the גמרא can raise this issue of
does it have to do with being defendable or not defendable, מיגנו
or not מיגנו, tying back into these types of initial historical circumstances.
So that's I just wanted to present you the thesis. There's a
lot of questions you can ask about that but one of the
places he anchors it is in this discussion of מיגנו, is it
a protected walled city, and he sees that that's why walled cities
were significant that the threat from the enemy was from the outside
and the Jews in the walled city therefore felt less under the
entire threat of what was happening with the פורים story. Yeah I
know there's a lot of questions to ask on that but let's
not I just wanted to give it to you. You have a
question on the גמרא? Yeah okay I understand this idea of a
open to the sea wall not being protected, being defendable. What
do you mean because you can have both that attack or whatever.
Well I guess first of all it depends I don't know what
the story with טבריה Tverya is. Is there a is it a
cliff is it a port can boats land? It's a beach it's
a beach it goes right down to the... Oh that's true of
course right right right. It's like Tel Aviv it's like built up
right against the water and so what?
Yeah yeah that's a good point. There's more of a cliff that
would function as a wall. Yeah and also the the idea of
the kind of בולי שורי bulei shorei isn't like the classic יריחו
Yericho wasn't רחב's Rachav house? They built it into the wall but
I think this one thing about first fundamentally building a wall and
then building houses into a wall or fundamentally building houses and the
wall sort of just emerges from the wall the house but yeah
I was thinking the same question about the whole יריחו Yericho story.
All right so let's continue. So the גמרא says like this. רב
אשי קרא מגילה בהוצא בארבעה עשר ובחמשה עשר. Rav Ashi kare Megillah
behutzo be-arba-asar u-ve-hamisha-asar. So now we're dealing with the question of which
cities you know and doubtful cities and so on are walled or
not walled from the time of יהושע. Yehoshua.
So רב אשי Rav Ashi read it on the 14th and the
15th in הוצא, Hutzo, מספקא ליה אם מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן
נון היא או לא, maspka leh im mukafit homa mi-yemot Yehoshua bin
Nun hi o lo, whether it was from the time of יהושע
Yehoshua or not it had a wall but how old was the
wall. גמרא says איכא דאמרי ika de-amri some say אמר רב אשי
האי הוצא דבי בנימין מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון היא. amar
Rav Ashi hai hutzo d'vei Binyamin mukafit homa mi-yemot Yehoshua bin Nun
hi. He had no question it was from the time of יהושע
Yehoshua בן נון. So maybe the story about him reading on the
14th wasn't correct. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan said רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan or a different unless it's a different הוצא. Hutzo. כי
הוינא טליא Ki havina talya when I was a kid I mean
טליא talya means like a lamb so it's like almost like a
kid goat but it's a lamb anyway. So when I was just
a kid אמינא מילתא דשאילנא לסבייא amina milta dishailna le-savaya I said
an idea and then I asked the elders top of ו עמוד
א vav amud aleph והשתכח כוותי ve-hishtakach kevasi
and it was discovered that my idea was correct. What was my
idea? How to identifying the different some of the different places that
we have listed in the פסוק pasuk in יהושע earlier about that
were walled cities. חמת זו טבריה, Chamat zu Tverya, חמת Chamat that
was a walled city that's טבריה. Tverya. ולמה נקרא שמה חמת? Velama
nikra shema Chamat? Why was it called חמת? Chamat? על שום חמי
טבריה Al shum hamei Tverya
because of the hot springs of טבריה. Tverya רקת Rakat which was
another פסוק pasuk city mentioned זו ציפורי zu Tzipori that's ציפורי. Tzipori.
ולמה נקרא
שמה רקת? Velama nikra shema Rakat? I know but the גמרא is
going to reverse. ולמה נקרא שמה רקת? Velama nikra shema Rakat? Why
was it called רקת? Rakat? משום דמדליה כריקתא דנהרא mishum de-midalya ke-rikta
de-nahara because ציפורי Tzipori is like high up on a mountain and
therefore it's raised up
like the bank of a river is raised up from the river.
כנרת זו גינוסר Kinneret zu Ginnosar and כנרת Kinneret is גינוסר Ginnosar
which is כנרת. Kinneret. ולמה נקרא שמה כנרת? Velama nikra shema Kinneret?
Why is it called כנרת? Kinneret? דמתיקי פירותיה כקלא דקינרי dematiki peiraheha
ke-kala de-kinri its fruit are so sweet like the sound of a
harp. Right some also say because like the כנרת Kinneret is somewhat
harp shaped might be why it's actually called כנרת. Kinneret. Okay anyway
אמר רבא מי איכא למאן דאמר רקת לאו טבריה היא? Amar Rava
mi ika leman de-amar Rakat lav Tverya hi? Now רבא Rava says
one minute you said חמת Chamat is טבריה Tverya. but we were
saying on the previous דף daf that רקת Rakat is טבריה Tverya
and who could be the person how could you claim that רקת
Rakat is not
טבריה Tverya דהא אשלח. deha ashalach. התם hatam ספדתי ליה הכי. safstei
lei hachi. Here is
how they eulogize a death that occurs here in טבריה. Tverya. גדול
הוא בששך ושם לו ברקת. Gadol hu be-Sheshach ve-shem lo be-Rakas. He
is great in ששך Sheshach which is a name in the תנ"ך
Tanakh for בבל Bavel and he has made for himself a name
in רקת. Rakas. So רקת Rakas apparently טבריה Tverya. was a place
where there were a lot of תלמידי חכמים talmidei chakhamim and so
on. So this person was so great apparently when a רב great,
רבי rabbi dies, this is the type of הספד that they say
over
in טבריה. Tverya. וכי מסקי ארונא להתם Ve-chi maskei arona le-hatam and
when the ארון aron gets there to טבריה Tverya. ספדתי ליה הכי
safstei lei hachi here is how they eulogize him. אוהבי שרידים Ohavei
seridim those the lovers of the remnant, meaning I guess אוהבי שרידים
ohavei seridim of the Jewish people, יושבי רקת yoshvei Rakas those who
dwell in רקת, Rakas, צאו וקבלו הרוגי עומק. tzu ve-kiblu harugei omek.
Go out and receive those that were killed in the valley. Now
again I do not know what this word is. רש"י Rashi does
not comment on it. הרוגי harugei slaughter, killed? I mean maybe it
was a natural death. But anyway עומק omek is because בבל Bavel
is low-lying land so it is called the valley. The point is
first of all you see that their הספדים were not telling stories
of the people's lives, they were very poetic and so on. But
anyway the point is that they are referring to themselves as רקת.
Rakas. So you see טבריה Tverya. is רקת. Rakas. Now we are
going to have a couple of other stories along this way and
then get back to the question. כי נח נפשיה דרבי זירא Ki
nach nafshia de-Rabbi Zeira when רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira died פתח עליה
ההוא ספדנא patach alei hahu safdana a certain eulogizer opened up with
the following eulogy. ארץ שנער הרה וילדה Eretz Shinar hara ve-yalada the
land of
שנער Shinar בבל Bavel became pregnant and gave birth because he was
born in בבל. Bavel. ארץ צבי גידלה שעשועיה Eretz Tzvi gidla sha'ashueha
the deer land, the precious land ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, raised its
beloved one, because רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was born in בבל Bavel
but then moved to ארץ ישראל. אוי נא לה אמרה רקת כי
אבדה כלי חמדתה Oy na la amra Rakas ki avda kli chemdatana
apparently he lived in טבריה. Tverya. Woe says רקת Rakas because it
has lost its precious vessel. Okay anyway all of this is you
see רקת Rakas is טבריה. Tverya. Very nice poetic הספד but you
see רקת Rakas is טבריה. Tverya? אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava
so rather רבא Rava says this idea that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says I said this great thing and I was right, you are
not right. אמר רבא Amar Rava חמת Khamas חמת Khamas is not
טבריה. Tverya? חמת זו חמי גדר. Khamas zu Chamei Gader. That
is the hot springs of גדר. Gader. אבימלך Avimelech מלך גרר? melech
Gerar? I guess. Yeah. I do not know where גרר Gerar is
and if it has a wall. רקת זו טבריה. Rakas zu Tverya.
רקת Rakas is טבריה. Tverya כנרת זו גינוסר Kinneret zu Ginosar as
you said כנרת Kinneret is גינוסר. Ginosar. ולמה נקרא שמה רקת? Ve-lama
nikra shema Rakas? So now we have to explain the identification of
רקת Rakas with טבריה. Tverya, שאפילו ריקנים שבה מלאים מצוות כרימון. She-afilu
reikanim she-ba mele'im mitzvot ke-rimon.
And this gets back to this idea that we have seen that
apparently גדולי תורה gedolei Torah either lived in there רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira or came to be buried there so it was a city
of a lot of learning. That even the empty people in רקת
Rakas are filled with מצוות mitzvot as a
pomegranate. רבי ירמי אמר רקת שמה. Rabbi Yirmi amar Rakas shema. No,
רקת Rakas is just the name it was given. It is a
proper name so you do not look for symbolism. That is its
name. The nickname is טבריה. ולמה נקרא שמה טבריה? Ve-lama nikra shema
Tverya? Why was it given the additional name of טבריה? שיושבת בטיבורה
של ארץ ישראל. She-yoshevet be-tibura shel Eretz Yisrael. It dwells like in
the belly button, in the center of the land of Israel. רבא
אמר רקת שמה. Rava amar Rakas shema. רבא Rava similarly says רקת
Rakas was its initial name. ולמה נקרא שמה טבריה? Ve-lama nikra shema
Tverya? Why was it called טבריה? שטובה ראייתה. She-tova re'iyata. So like
the word טוב ראי. tov re'i. Like its appearance is good. It
has a good rapport, obviously it was a very prestigious city. אמר
זעירי. Amar Ze'iri. Okay now that we have identified those cities in
terms of walled cities, now we are going to do some more.
קטרון Kitron as
we will see in a minute from a פסוק pasuk in שופטים
Shoftim זו ציפורי zu Tzipori is ציפורי. Tzipori. So we said רקת
Rakas was ציפורי. Tzipori. Now that we are saying רקת Rakas is
טבריה we need to find where ציפורי Tzipori is. So we need
to locate ציפורי Tzipori again. So קטרון Kitron is ציפורי. Tzipori. ולמה
נקרא שמה ציפורי? Ve-lama nikra shema Tzipori? And why was it given
the name ציפורי? Tzipori? שיושבת בראשה של ציפור. She-yoshevet be-rosho shel tzippur.
It is on the top of a mountain like a bird. וקטרון
ציפורי היא? ve-Kitron Tzipori hi? Now one minute, you are telling me
קטרון Kitron is ציפורי? Tzipori? והא קטרון בחלקו של זבולון הוה. Ve-ha
Kitron be-chelko shel Zvulun hava. קטרון Kitron was in the portion of
זבולון. Zvulun. דכתיב and now we are going to see where the
word קטרון Kitron comes up. זבולון
לא הוריש את יושבי קטרון. Zvulun lo horish et yoshvei Kitron. זבולון
Zvulun never fully dispossessed those who dwelt in קטרון. Kitron. They remained
living in their land. ואת יושבי נהלול. ve-et yoshvei Nahalol. Okay so
now how do I know that קטרון Kitron is not ציפורי? Tzipori?
Okay good it is in זבולון Zvulun so maybe that was ציפורי.
Tzipori. What does that tell me that it is not ציפורי? Tzipori?
So now we are going to tell a story that will show
that קטרון Kitron being in זבולון's חלק Zvulun's chelek cannot be ציפורי.
Tzipori. זבולון Zvulun very famous sort of גמרא... here מתרעם על מדותיו
היה. Mitra'em al middosav hayah. זבולון Zvulun was complaining about their portion,
you know, about what they were given in their portion of the
land. שנאמר: She'ne'emar: זבולון עם חרף נפשו למות. Zvulun am charaf nafsho
lamut. This is from שירת דבורה. Shirat Devorah. זבולון, Zvulun, a people
that shamed their soul to die. So obviously in the שירה, Shirah,
it's like a praise, right? That they're willing to be courageous and
put their lives on the line in the war. But here it's
reading it in the negative, חרף נפשו. charaf nafsho. מה טעם? Mah
ta'am? Why would they sort of, you know, being like cursing is
the way it's reading? Because of ונפתלי על מרומי שדה, ve'Naftali al
meromei sadeh, the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Because נפתלי Naftali got
the wonderful fields. אמר זבולון לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Zvulun lifnei
HaKadosh Baruch Hu, זבולון Zvulun says to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono
shel Olam, Master of the Universe, לאחי, le'achi, to my brother there
נפתלי, Naftali, נתת להם שדות וכרמים, natata lahem sadot u'chramim, you gave
them fields and vineyards. ולי, ve'li, what about me? נתת הרים וגבעות,
natata harim u'gva'ot, you gave mountains and hills. What can you do
with mountains and hills? You can't plant, it's not good for agriculture.
ולי... ve'li... Where's valley? Where's valley? Oh, I'm sorry, not valleys, mountains
and hills. He didn't give us a valley. Yes, true, valleys you
can plant, excuse me. Excuse me. Excuse me. Mountains and hills, thank
you, sorry. לאחי, le'achi, to my brother, נתת להם ארצות, natata lahem
aratzot, you gave them land like a good, you know, real estate,
property to plant on. ולי, ve'li, me? נתת ימים ונהרות, natata yamim
u'neharot, what do I get? I get rivers, I get, I get
oceans, I get seas. What good is any of that? אמר לו,
Amar lo, so God said... man, not understanding the importance of a
port city. Anyway, אמר לו, Amar lo, so God said back to
him, כולם צריכין לך, kulam tzrichin lach, everybody is going to want,
going to need you, you're going to have, you know, because of
where you're situated. על ידי חלזון, al yedei chalazon, first of all
you're going to be from the, you know, you're going to have
the חלזון chalazon from the snails or whatever it's from, you know,
you're going to have the blue that you need for this תכלת.
techelet. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, the verse says, עמים הר יקראו, Amim har yikra'u,
nations will be, you know, will be called to the mountains. This
is from the, from the, you know, שירה Shirah in דברים about,
you know, and ושפוני טמוני חול, u'sefunei tmunei chol, right, and this
is about זבולון Zvulun and the what hidden treasures, you know, in
the sand. So everybody's going to come to the mountains of זבולון
Zvulun and to come to you because you'll have what comes, you
know, what's the things that are hidden in the sands, the snails
that get deposited, what, you know, in the sand from the sea
that you make the חלזון chalazon from. תני רב יוסף, Tani Rav
Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef taught, שפוני, sefunei, זו חלזון, zu chalazon,
hidden is the חלזון. chalazon. טמוני, tmunei, זו טרית, zu tarit, is
טרית, tarit, which רש"י says is תנינא, tunina, so I guess it's
tuna. What does it really mean by buried though? I don't get
that either. It must mean that there had been an ocean there.
You know how you walk in the נגב Negev and you find
seashells? So that must be what I mean... no, that's not to
the tuna fish, that might be the chalazon. The טמון tamun is
the tuna fish. Yeah, you're talking about, you don't understand the tuna?
Yeah, how can a tuna be hidden? What's it hidden from? It's
down in the ocean, it's hidden. Okay. חול, chol, זו זכוכית, zu
zechuchit, and חול chol is the glass that you make from sand.
לבנה, levanah, the very pure white glass which is very precious in
those days. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, and they had a very clean
sand that you could make this precious white glass from. So he
says stop complaining, you'll make your money not in, you know, not
in farming, you have plenty of ways to make money. אמר לפניו,
Amar lefanav, so זבולון Zvulun said to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono
shel Olam, Master of the Universe, מי מודיעני, mi modia'ni, who's going
to inform me? What am I going to do to stop people
who want to try to like steal the snails, you know? How
do I protect the, you know, this? אמר לו, Amar lo, so
God said to him, שם יזבחו זבחי צדק, sham yizbechu zivchei tzedek,
there they will bring sacrifices of righteousness. סימן זה יהיה לך, siman
zeh yihiyeh lach, this will be a סימן siman for you, כל
הנוטל ממך בלא דמים, kol hanotel mimcha belo damim, if anybody steals
any of the stuff without paying for it, אינו מועיל בפרקמטיא שלו,
eino mo'il bifrakmatya shelo, their business will not succeed. Exactly where you
get that from the פסוק? pasuk? צדק, tzedek, righteousness, תוספות says because
you can't bring קרבנות korbanot from גזל. gezel. Anyway, don't worry about
it, you'll be protected. כלומר, klomar, now, now how is all of
that relevant? So we see זבולון Zvulun complaining, and we said that
that this city that was קטרון Kitron which is in זבולון Zvulun
is ציפורי. Tzipori. So the גמרא's question is going to be, if
they had ציפורי Tzipori in their חלק, chelek, they would have had
no reason to complain to begin with. ואי סלקא דעתך קטרון זו
ציפורי, ve'i salka daitach Kitron zu Tzipori, if קטרון Kitron was ציפורי...
Tzipori... I said טבריה, I meant ציפורי, Tzipori, excuse me. קטרון Kitron
is ציפורי. Tzipori. So if קטרון Kitron was ציפורי, Tzipori, if they
started with ציפורי Tzipori in their חלק, chelek, אמאי מתרעם על מדותיו,
amai mitra'em al middosav, why would they have any basis to complain?
והא ציפורי מילתא דעדיפא טובא, ve'ha Tzipori milta de'adifa tuva, ציפורי Tzipori
is a wonderful, it's an amazing city. So obviously they couldn't have
started with ציפורי Tzipori because then they wouldn't have been able to
complain at the beginning. וכי תימא דלית בה זבת חלב ודבש, ve'chi
teima de'leit bah zavat chalav u'dvash, maybe it's a wonderful city but
maybe it's not flowing with milk and honey, it doesn't have all
the qualities. והאמר ריש לקיש, ve'ha'amar Reish Lakish, now again the גמרא
treats this זבת חלב ודבש zavat chalav u'dvash in a very literal
sense. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said, לדידי חזי לי זבת חלב ודבש
דציפורי, le'didi chazi li zavat chalav u'dvash de'Tzipori, I saw the flowing
with milk and honey of ציפורי. Tzipori. flowing of milk and honey
in ציפורי *Tzippori*, והוי שיתסר מיל אשיתסר מיל *ve-havei shiteisar mil a-shiteisar
mil*, it was sixteen kilometers by sixteen kilometers, so presumably now the
גמרא *Gemara* says what does... the גמרא *Gemara* in one place says
what does flowing with milk and honey mean? It claims it's not
a metaphor but what it means is that you've got the goats
that are eating like the, you know, the dates, and their udders
are so filled with milk and their udders sort of like go
against the ground and the milk comes out and the date juice
comes out which is the honey because it's date honey and it's
flowing with milk and honey. And the גמרא *Gemara* here seems also
to be translating this in a very literal sense. It is flowing
with milk and honey, huge sixteen by sixteen kilometers. וכי תימא דלא
נפישי דידה כדאחוה *ve-khi teima de-lo nefishei deideh ke-de-acha-hu*, maybe fine it's
flowing with milk and honey but not as
much as the other שבטים *shevatim*? That can't be. ואמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן לדידי חזי לי זבת חלב ודבש דכל
ארץ ישראל *ve-amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan le-didi chazei
li zavat chalav u-devash de-khol Eretz Yisrael*, I saw the area covered
that was flowing in milk and honey, again I don't know what
you do with these גמרות *Gemarot* in the entire land of Israel,
והויא כמבי כובי עד אקרא דתולבכני *ve-haveya ki-mi-bei Kubi ad Akra de-Tulbakni*,
and it was the distance from בי כובי *Bei Kubi* to אקרא
דתולבכני *Akra de-Tulbakni*, of this place, אקרא דתולבכני *Akra de-Tulbakni*. And what
was that? עשרין ותרתין פרסי *esrin ve-tartin parsei*, twenty-two parsangs, a פרסא
*parsa* is four מיל *mil*, or of its length, ופותיה שיתא פרסי
*u-futya shita parsei*, six parsangs, so you do the math anyway and
what זבולון *Zevulun* gets is more than one twelfth of that. So
they had זבת חלב ודבש *zavat chalav u-devash*, it was more than
the normal share that the rest of the שבטים *shevatim* got, and
they had ציפורי *Tzippori*, so what were they complaining about? So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, אפילו הכי שדות וכרמים עדיפא ליה *afilu hakhi sadot
u-khramim adifa leh*, it doesn't matter how good they had it, they
were focused on the field and the vineyard and they were complaining
that they didn't have fields and vineyards, they couldn't appreciate everything else
they had. That's part of the whole story. דיקא נמי דכתיב *deika
nami de-khtiv*, that also can be inferred because it says, ונפתלי על
רמות שדה *ve-Naftali al ramot sadeh*, what was bothering them was that
נפתלי *Naftali* had the one thing that they didn't have. That you
know that's always what bothers you. It's not what you have but
what somebody else has that you don't have. So that's what bothered
them, that they didn't have fields. שמע מינה *shema mina*. And that
allows us to come to a peace with the idea that ציפורי
*Tzippori* is this place of what was it called again in זבולון
*Zevulun*, this place of קטרון *Kitron*. Okay, fine. Now we got that
figured out. Moving on. אמר רבי אבהו *amar Rabbi Abbahu*, since we
mentioned עקרון *Ekron*, let's look at another פסוק pasuk *pasuk* by עקרון
*Ekron* in צפניה *Tzephaniah*. ועקרון תעקר *ve-Ekron te-aker*, עקרון *Ekron* will be
uprooted. זו קיסרי בת אדום zu Keisari bat Edom, *zu Keisari bat
Edom*, that is Caesarea, the daughter of אדום Edom, *Edom* because you
know Caesarea was an outpost of the Roman Empire. שהיא יושבת בין
החולות *she-hi yoshevet bein ha-cholot*, that's between the sands, right, because it's
there on the coast. שהיא היתה יתד תקועה לישראל בימי יוונים *she-hi
hayeta yated teku-ah le-Yisrael bi-yemei Yevanim*, that was like we would say
a thorn in the side, here it's like a peg in the
side, a thorn stuck in the side of Israel in the time
of the Greeks, you know, from Hellenists, the Roman Empire, okay. וכשגברה
מלכות בית חשמונאי ונצחום *ve-khshe-gavra malkhut beit Chashmonai ve-nitzchum*, or the pre-Roman
Empire, whatever, the Greeks, you know, because you have חשמונאים Chashmonaim. *Chashmonaim*,
and when the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim* were victorious and presumably they took over
Caesarea, היו קוראים אותה אחידת מגדל שיר *hayu korim otah achidat migdal
shir*, they called it the conquered, you know, tower of שיר *shir*.
There's interesting speculations about what that means, what that name is referring
to. Anyway, that was a thing that was a Roman outpost, you
know, and that in the end and it was conquered in the
time of the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim*.
Okay, so it was an outpost before, you know, even before. אמר
רבי יוסי בר חנינא *amar Rabbi Yosei bar Chanina*, מאי דכתיב *mai
de-khtiv*, what's meant by the verse, והסירותי דמיו מפיו ושקוציו מבין שניו
*ve-hasiroti damav mi-piv ve-shikutzav mi-bein shinav*, I will remove the blood from
their mouth and the abomination from their teeth, ונשאר גם הוא לאלוהינו
*ve-nishar gam hu l-Eloheinu*, and they will remain for our God. So
והסירותי דמיו מפיו *ve-hasiroti damav mi-piv*, זו בית במיא שלהן *zu beit
bamya shelahen*, that is so again we're now that we're talking about
אדום Edom, *Edom* and Rome and so on and how in the
end these things turn over to the Jewish people, right, and that
was the issue of Caesarea, we're going to have a similar type
of דרשות drashot *drashot*. Okay, so this is their the places of
their altars, of their sacrificial altars. ושקוציו מבין שניו *ve-shikutzav mi-bein shinav*,
the abomination from between its teeth, זו בית גליא שלהן *zu beit
galya shelahen*. Now some say that's another name of an idolatrous location,
but some want to say that that means their oracles, like לגלות
*legalot*, to reveal, the places of their oracles. I think that's an
interesting interpretation.
ביהודה *bi-Yehuda*, that exists in יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda*. ועקרון כביבוסי *ve-Ekron ke-Yevusi*,
and ונשאר גם הוא...
I'm sorry, I skipped a line. Where are we? ושלהן, ונשאר גם
הוא, I skipped on that line, thank you, ונשאר גם הוא לאלוהינו
*ve-nishar gam hu l-Eloheinu*, and they will remain for our God. What
does that mean? אלו בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות שבאדום *elu batei khenesiyot
u-vatei midrashot she-be-Edom*, that in the Roman Empire there are houses of
study and synagogues. So those will be the things that will remain
and all the idolatrous stuff, that will be completely uprooted. Okay, so
again right now we're under Rome and so on, all these things
are bad, but they it was reversed before, like this case of
Caesarea, and these things end up. will be reversed in the future.
Okay, now the גמרא got to this of course because of this
whole thing of תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, but I always ask myself
like is there some function of particularly putting these אגדתא aggadata like
where they are in this גמרא. And you know I do think
it's just worth noting that right מגילה, the problem of מגילה, the
problem of the חג chag is a quote-unquote problem is like the
גמרא says why don't we say הלל Hallel because אכתי עבדי אחשורוש
אנן. akati avdei Achashveirosh anan.
It was like the one חג chag that didn't result in a
historical change of like Jew, you know, the Jews now are like
self-ruled,
that we're now, we've changed our historical circumstances. What happened was we
got rid of an imminent threat. You know, Jewish history is cases
of having threats and sometimes managing to avoid those threats, sadly sometimes
not. But the basic historical circumstances remain the same, right? Even חנוכה
was a profound change of the historical circumstances, right? Where now they
were free from, you know, from the external control, at least for
a while. So I think that in that context it's interesting that
you have these אגדתא aggadata which sort of acknowledge that we are
still, you know, a subjugated people under Rome, but like you know
looking forward to the time where all of that will eventually reverse.
But in a way that's sort of like the poignant aspect about
פורים is that we still remain subjugated. And here are these sort
of דרשות drashot, that are dealing to some, you know, so with
that, with that reality, that are very much descriptive of that reality.
So let's look at another one. והיה כאלוף ביהודה ועקרון כיבוסי Vehaya
ke-aluf bi-Yehuda ve-Ekron ke-Yevusi
and they will be like a like you know an like like
a prince in יהודה and עקרון כיבוסי Ekron ke-Yevusi we'll see what
that means. אלו תרטיאות וקרקסיאות שבאדום, elu teratiyot ve-kirkasiyot she-be-Edom,
these are the theaters and the circuses that are in Rome. שעתידים
שרי יהודה ללמד בהם תורה
ברבים, she-atidim sarei Yehuda le-lamed ba-hem Torah ba-rabbim, they're going to, I
mean they're great, there's these big auditoriums. So those are going to
be places where we're going to give big דרשות, they'll turn into
בתי מדרשות, batei midrashot, that's just what's going to happen to them.
So somehow the word, רש"י says עקרון כיבוסי Ekron ke-Yevusi
that יבוסי Yevusi is ירושלים Yerushalayim because ירושלים Yerushalayim was originally, right,
the city of the Yevusite, etc. So anyway, it'll be like ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, they'll revert, you know, they will become these big theaters and
circuses will become places of learning תורה. Torah. אמר רבי יצחק. Amar
Rabbi Yitzchak.
So now says רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. לשם זו פמיאס. Leshem zu
Pameyas. לשם Leshem is פמיאס Pameyas
which is presumably the Banias. עקרון תעקר, Ekron te-aker, the verse of
עקרון תעקר, Ekron te-aker, זו קיסרי Keisari, בת אדום,
this is Caesarea, שהיתה מטרופולין של מלכים, she-hayita metropolis shel melachim, it
was a metropolis of kings. We'll see what that means. What does
that mean of kings? איכא דאמרי דמרבי בה מלכים, ika de-amrei de-merabi
ba melachim, some say that it means that kings were raised there,
like you know maybe the princes were sent there to, you know,
to go to school or something. ואיכא דאמרי דמוקמי מינה מלכי, ve-ika
de-amrei de-mokeimi minah malchei,
and that you know kings were appointed from there, that from that
population is primarily where the kings were drawn from. Anyway, this was,
you know, very nice to say that קיסרי, Keisari right there in
ארץ ישראל, that's where the kings came or the I don't know
the Caesars came for Rome. But anyway, קיסרי Keisari and ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Now we're going to deal with this now that so that eventually
will be uprooted, right? עקרון תעקר. Ekron te-aker. And now we're going
to so and now we're going to go back again to that
theme, so קיסרי Keisari represents sort of like Rome and eventually it'll
be uprooted, it'll turn over to us, we'll conquer it like we
did in the time of the חשמונאים. The theaters will become places
of תורה. Torah. And now we're going to deal with this again
this sort of competition of Rome and Jerusalem. Rome and Israel. Through
the representative cities of קיסרי and
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. קיסרי וירושלים. Keisari ve-Yerushalayim. So these two cities. אם יאמר
לך אדם חרבו שתיהן im yomar lecha adam charvu shteihem if a
person says both are destroyed, אל תאמן, al ta'amen, do not believe.
ישבו שתיהן, yashvu shteihem, both of them are settled, they're both successful
cities, אל תאמן, al ta'amen, don't believe. חרבה קיסרי וישבה ירושלים, charva
Keisari ve-yashva Yerushalayim, Caesarea is destroyed, Jerusalem is inhabited and settled, or
חרבה ירושלים וישבה קיסרי, charva Yerushalayim ve-yashva Keisari, or Jerusalem is destroyed
and Caesarea settled, תאמן, ta'amen, you should believe it. שנאמר אמלאה החרבה,
she-ne'emar imalei hacharava, I will I will fill the desolate place. אם
מלאה זו חרבה זו, im maleia zu charava zu, one if one
is one is fulfilled, filled, one is, you know, established, the other
is destroyed. אם מלאה זו חרבה זו, im maleia zu charava zu,
and if the other one is filled then the then the first
one is destroyed. So Jerusalem and, you know, and Caesarea, Israel and
and אדום, you know, and אדום, ultimately who's Israel and and, you
know, who's who they go back to? יעקב ועשו, Yaakov ve-Esav, right?
So those are in the constant eternal sort of conflict. And one
will always be victorious and the other not. They cannot both be
victorious at the same time. So ultimately it's getting back to the
point, yes, right now we're still subjugated under, you know, the Roman
Empire. But in the end, it's going to reverse itself. We'll be
on the top and they'll be on the bottom. And let's just
read one more פסוק
about them, sorry, of ולאם מלאם יאמץ u'leom mi'leom ye'ematz getting back
explicitly to יעקב Yaakov and עשו, Eisav, so one will be against
the other and therefore it'll be, you know, יעקב Yaakov and עשו
Eisav will constantly be in competition. Okay, we'll have to end here.
What David, you have a final point?